<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: shell | Terminal Curiosity]]></title>
  <link href="http://erichs.github.io/blog/categories/shell/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://erichs.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-22T10:20:55-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://erichs.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Erich Smith]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Colored Glasses for Less]]></title>
    <link href="http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/22/colored-glasses-for-less/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-22T09:51:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/22/colored-glasses-for-less</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Eine kleine Probleme</h2>

<p>Sometimes you&rsquo;ll want to view some output in less, the default PAGER, and you&rsquo;ll realize that the output was colorized with ANSI escape sequences.</p>

<!-- more -->


<p>To demonstrate the issue, I&rsquo;ll run a ruby file (example taken from <a href="https://github.com/docopt/docopt.rb">docopt</a>) through pygmentize:</p>

<p><code>bash
$ pygmentize -l ruby naval.rb | less
</code></p>

<p>which produces:</p>

<pre>
ESC[36mrequireESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00mESC[33m"ESC[39;49;00mESC[33mdocoptESC[39;49;00mESC[33m"ESC[39;49;00m
docESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00m=ESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00m<<ESC[39;49;00mESC[31mDOCOPTESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33mNaval Fate.ESC[39;49;00m

ESC[33mUsage:ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  #{__FILE__} ship new <name>...ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  #{__FILE__} ship <name> move <x> <y> [--speed=<kn>]ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  #{__FILE__} ship shoot <x> <y>ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  #{__FILE__} mine (set|remove) <x> <y> [--moored|--drifting]ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  #{__FILE__} -h | --helpESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  #{__FILE__} --versionESC[39;49;00m

ESC[33mOptions:ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  -h --help     Show this screen.ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  --version     Show version.ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  --speed=<kn>  Speed in knots [default: 10].ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  --moored      Moored (anchored) mine.ESC[39;49;00m
ESC[33m  --drifting    Drifting mine.ESC[39;49;00m

ESC[31mDOCOPTESC[39;49;00m

ESC[34mbeginESC[39;49;00m
  ESC[39;49;00mESC[36mrequireESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00mESC[33m"ESC[39;49;00mESC[33mppESC[39;49;00mESC[33m"ESC[39;49;00m
    ESC[39;49;00mppESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00mESC[33mDocoptESC[39;49;00m:ESC[39;49;00mESC[33m:docoptESC[39;49;00m(ESC[39;49;00mdocESC[39;49;00m)ESC[39;49;00m
    ESC[34mrescueESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00mESC[33mDocoptESC[39;49;00m:ESC[39;49;00mESC[33m:ExitESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00m=ESC[39;49;00m>ESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00meESC[39;49;00m
      ESC[39;49;00mESC[36mputsESC[39;49;00m ESC[39;49;00meESC[39;49;00m.ESC[39;49;00mmessageESC[39;49;00m
      ESC[34mendESC[39;49;00m
      (END)]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]])]]]]]]]]]"]]]]"]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]]"]]]]"]]]]
</pre>


<h2>Keine Probleme!</h2>

<p>Of course, you could have invoked less with <code>-r: display raw control characters</code>, but what to do after the fact, when you&rsquo;ve got a steaming pile of escape sequences staring back at you?</p>

<p>Less supports entering flags from the <code>:</code> prompt. So just type the following literal key sequence to enter raw character mode:</p>

<p><code>:--r</code></p>

<p>That&rsquo;s colon, dash, dash, r.</p>

<p>Now your less output looks like:</p>

<pre>
<span style="color:teal;">require</span> <span style="color:olive;">&quot;</span><span style="color:olive;">docopt</span><span style="color:olive;">&quot;</span>
doc = &lt;&lt;<span style="color:red;">DOCOPT</span>
<span style="color:olive;">Naval Fate.</span>

<span style="color:olive;">Usage:</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  #{__FILE__} ship new &lt;name&gt;...</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  #{__FILE__} ship &lt;name&gt; move &lt;x&gt; &lt;y&gt; [--speed=&lt;kn&gt;]</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  #{__FILE__} ship shoot &lt;x&gt; &lt;y&gt;</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  #{__FILE__} mine (set|remove) &lt;x&gt; &lt;y&gt; [--moored|--drifting]</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  #{__FILE__} -h | --help</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  #{__FILE__} --version</span>

<span style="color:olive;">Options:</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  -h --help     Show this screen.</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  --version     Show version.</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  --speed=&lt;kn&gt;  Speed in knots [default: 10].</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  --moored      Moored (anchored) mine.</span>
<span style="color:olive;">  --drifting    Drifting mine.</span>

<span style="color:red;">DOCOPT</span>

<span style="color:blue;">begin</span>
  <span style="color:teal;">require</span> <span style="color:olive;">&quot;</span><span style="color:olive;">pp</span><span style="color:olive;">&quot;</span>
  pp <span style="color:olive;">Docopt</span>:<span style="color:olive;">:docopt</span>(doc)
<span style="color:blue;">rescue</span> <span style="color:olive;">Docopt</span>:<span style="color:olive;">:Exit</span> =&gt; e
  <span style="color:teal;">puts</span> e.message
<span style="color:blue;">end</span>
</pre>



]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bundling binary blobs]]></title>
    <link href="http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/19/bundling-binary-blobs/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-19T09:02:53-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/19/bundling-binary-blobs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every once in a blue moon, the following hack comes in handy, and I have to look it up again. I don&rsquo;t remember where I first saw this technique in the wild, but I remember being blown away when I realized what was going on.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Effect</h2>

<p>A grizzled neckbeard hands you a shell script, and tells you to run it, and that it will install the application you&rsquo;ve been wanting to try out.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;What?&rdquo; you say. &ldquo;Does it download it from the Internet?&rdquo;</p></p><p><p>&ldquo;No. No network required.&rdquo;</p></p><p><p>&ldquo;What, do I run this with Java, or something?&rdquo;</p></p><p><p>&ldquo;No, it is self-contained.&rdquo;</p></p><p><p>&ldquo;Do I need to type a cryptic command sequence to get this to run?&rdquo;</p></p><p><p>Look, please just run the script. It will install your application.&ldquo;</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Then you look at the file, and see that it is several megabytes long. And, sure enough, it installs your shiny new app. But how?</p>

<h2>Preparation</h2>

<p>You will need:</p>

<ul>
<li>a <code>tar</code>ed and <code>gzip</code>ped file containing the source or binary distribution you want to bundle</li>
<li>knowledge of which additional commands to run, if any, to compile, install or otherwise deal with the unpacked files</li>
<li>an open mind</li>
</ul>


<h2>Method</h2>

<p>You will be creating a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Self-extracting_archive">self-extracting executable</a>. The fact that the <strong>&lsquo;executable&rsquo;</strong> portion is really <strong>interpreted shell script</strong>, is irrelevant. This technique hinges on the ability of the shell script to reference itself, ignore the shell script portion, and feed the remainder to the shell script as binary data:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/01bb10aa16a80171358d.js?file=binary.sh'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/bash
sudo do_whatnot_first
tail -n +8 $0 | tar -zxf - -C /tmp
cd /tmp/my_extracted_tarfile_location
./configure &amp;&amp; make &amp;&amp; sudo make install
exit 0
#//EOF

$ cat myprog.tar.gz &gt;&gt; binary.sh</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>I actually don&rsquo;t prefer to use this version above, but the magic is easy to spot on line 3: <code>tail -n +8 $0</code>: <code>$0</code> is a reference to this, the current script file, so this command dumps line 8 through the end of the file through a pipeline to a <code>tar</code> extraction command. A careful count of the source reveals that line 8 is where the binary tar data was appended.</p>

<p>I don&rsquo;t like this version because you have to manually and carefully count the lines of code in your script and change line 3 accordingly. I much prefer the following snippet which is more robust, but perhaps a bit harder to follow:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/9cb8986fcd2bd4c11217.js?file=improved_binary.sh'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>#!/bin/bash
{
  cd /path/to/unzip || exit
  while read line do
    case $line in
    &quot;exit 0&quot;) break;;
    esac
  done
  gzip -dc | tar xf -
} &lt; &quot;$0&quot;
exit 0
&lt;...binary data here...&gt;</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>This version uses file redirection on <code>$0</code> to put the contents of the script through the whole shell block between curly braces, and uses a <code>while read</code> loop to pre-emptively throw away the lines of STDIN that correspond to the script preamble, before passing the remaining, binary data through tar. The <code>while</code> loop also cleverly uses the string matching capability of <code>case</code> to treat the <code>exit 0</code> as a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sentinel_value">sentinel value</a>. Thus, <code>exit 0</code> serves as both the start-of-data marker, and the end-of-script command. Wild.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Lightning Talk at Triangle.rb!]]></title>
    <link href="http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/13/lightning-talk-at-triangle-dot-rb/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-13T09:53:47-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/13/lightning-talk-at-triangle-dot-rb</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last night, I gave a <a href="http://www.meetup.com/raleighrb/events/194702002/">5-minute &ldquo;Lightning Talk&rdquo;</a> at <a href="http://www.triangleruby.com/">Triangle.rb</a>, entitled &ldquo;Compose with Confidence&rdquo;. Here are the slides and audio:</p>

<center><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/kd0ORVsJIL4" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></center>


<p>Someone asked what I used to generate the slides. I used <a href="https://github.com/egonSchiele/mdpress/">mdpress</a>, which in turn uses <a href="https://github.com/bartaz/impress.js/">impress.js</a> for the Prezi-like transitions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Compose with Confidence]]></title>
    <link href="http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/06/compose-with-confidence/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-06T10:30:02-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/08/06/compose-with-confidence</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/07/08/servant-of-two-masters/" title="Servant of Two Masters">Last time</a>, I noted that the experience of composing shell functions at the command prompt is awkward. Here&rsquo;s what works for me, and why.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>REPLs ❤ Pipes</h2>

<p>The shell command prompt is great for quick <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Read%E2%80%93eval%E2%80%93print_loop">REPL</a> feedback: run a command, watch
the output, tweak the command, and repeat until you have the output you desire.
This is a great way to build up complex command sequences. Feedback is
immediate, and the ability to recall and directly edit recent command history
encourages experimentation.</p>

<p>The prompt is no replacement for a full text editor, however, and there are times that you&rsquo;ll start a command at the prompt and <a href="http://nuclearsquid.com/writings/edit-long-commands/">wish you had done so in an editor</a>.</p>

<p>While available for short-term recall in terminal history, command sequences entered at the prompt have a short shelf-life. Shell functions defined (albeit painfully) at the prompt, for example, do not persist across shell invocations.</p>

<p>Composing a complex logic construct or shell function at the prompt is, at best, ephemeral and awkward.</p>

<h2>Scripts ❤ Functions</h2>

<p>Script <em>files</em> are the natural habitat for functions and larger programmatic constructs: after all, you have a full 2D editor environment in which to draft, save and revise your code. What might be a struggle and a chore to compose at the command prompt becomes easy inside a text editor.</p>

<p>Persisting to the filesystem means that you can bring all the tools for dealing
with files to bear on your script, including version control&mdash;critical to
maintaining code of any real complexity.</p>

<p>Script files have downsides, of course. Chief among them that you lose all the feedback from the command prompt&mdash;if you are creating a complex command sequence, you&rsquo;re flying blind inside the editor. Also, you&rsquo;ve just inherited all the file-related baggage required to get your script to actually run: shebang lines, executable bits, and PATH considerations.</p>

<p>Composing a complex logic construct or shell function in a script file feels natural, but loses the immediacy of the prompt and can sometimes feel too heavyweight: both factors which discourage the proliferation of lots of small shell functions, which as we&rsquo;ve seen can vastly improve the readability and maintainability of our command sequences.</p>

<h2>Best of both worlds?</h2>

<p>I care about readability in my shell code. If you&rsquo;re reading this, perhaps you do too. I wanted the best of both worlds, prompt <strong><em>and</em></strong> editor, so I wrote <a href="https://github.com/erichs/composure">composure, a set of opinionated shell functions that help you write shell functions</a>.</p>

<p>In a future post, I&rsquo;ll highlight a few of the features and benefits of writing shell functions with composure, and a few unexpected use cases I&rsquo;ve found.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Servant of Two Masters]]></title>
    <link href="http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/07/08/servant-of-two-masters/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-08T14:08:36-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://erichs.github.io/blog/2014/07/08/servant-of-two-masters</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="/blog/2014/06/30/broken-windows-and-broken-code/" title="Broken Windows and Broken Code">Last time</a>, I brought up the subject of fixing shell commands as you go along, and suggested that the practice of doing so could be good for your programmatic health. Today I&rsquo;d like to highlight an underused Unix command that does this well, and talk through the broader implications of its use.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>The <code>fc</code> utility</h2>

<p>First introduced via the Korn Shell, and a <a href="http://pubs.opengroup.org/onlinepubs/9699919799/utilities/fc.html">standard Unix utility</a> since at least the mid-90&rsquo;s, <code>fc</code> is short for &ldquo;fix command&rdquo;. Its purpose is to open up a previous command in the editor of your choice, and re-run the revised command once you are finished editing it.</p>

<p>With no arguments, <code>fc</code> will open the most previous command in the editor for editing and re-evaluation. In pure shell terms, it is roughly equivalent to:</p>

<p><code>bash I hope you'll agree, 'fc' is easier to type
echo !! &gt; /tmp/cmd &amp;&amp; $EDITOR /tmp/cmd &amp;&amp; eval $(cat /tmp/cmd); rm /tmp/cmd
</code></p>

<p>Most implementations of <code>fc</code> will use an editor specified in the <code>FCEDIT</code> environment variable, followed by <code>EDITOR</code>, then <code>vi</code>, and finally <code>ed</code>. You could of course launch an external editor like Sublime Text or Eclipse, but I find that keeping the editor inside the terminal feels most natural for this purpose.</p>

<p>I want to talk now about the experience of using a command like this. If you&rsquo;ve not used this utility before, go ahead and try it out a few times. Yes, right now. Seriously, I&rsquo;ll wait.</p>

<hr />


<center><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/9hmDZz5pDOQ" allowfullscreen></iframe></div></center>


<hr />


<h2>Context Switching</h2>

<p>So, kinda cool, but a little jarring, right? There you were happily plunking commands down at a prompt, and all of a sudden you&rsquo;re in your familiar editor, but perhaps in a slightly new context. Now you are editing your last command, say <code>ls -l</code>, as if it were a script:</p>

<p>``` bash</p>

<h1>!/bin/sh</h1>

<p>ls -l
```</p>

<p>Furthermore, the act of saving and quitting ran the script, back at your terminal.</p>

<h2>Two Environments, Two Adaptations</h2>

<p>I think the feeling of slight disorientation that occurs when using <code>fc</code> for the first time stems from inherent tension between the two modes of operation, or execution environments of the shell interpreter: the shell is at once the familiar REPL prompt we use all the time, and the shell is also the interpreter of script files.</p>

<h3>The Prompt</h3>

<p>We naturally adapt our shell behaviors, as users, to these different execution environments: the interactive, REPL-nature of the prompt means that we can run a quick command, and immediately see the output displayed to the terminal. Based on that output, we might decide to try a different command altogether, consult a man page, or perhaps just hit the up arrow and make a quick revision to our command.</p>

<p>In particular, using the shell prompt to build up complex command pipelines is invaluable: you get to see the output of each filter command:</p>

<script type="text/javascript" src="https://asciinema.org/a/10680.js" id="asciicast-10680" async data-speed="2"></script>


<p>At the prompt, this feels natural. You try a command, examine the output or result, add an appropriate filter command or commands until you have massaged the output into a desired format. You have the benefit of <strong>understandability</strong> as a <strong>writer</strong> of the command because the output of all the intermediate commands are available to you <strong>while</strong> you are writing.</p>

<h3>The Script</h3>

<p>Contrast that experience with encountering something like this in a script:</p>

<p>```bash Readability matters</p>

<h1>!/usr/bin/env bash</h1>

<p> netstat -p tcp | grep -i established | awk &lsquo;{print $5}&rsquo; | awk -F'.&lsquo; &rsquo;{ $NF=&ldquo;&rdquo; } 1' | sed &rsquo;s/ /./g' | sed &rsquo;s/.$//&lsquo; | sort | uniq
```</p>

<p>The above is simply unintelligible. Even if you are a regex master and know the syntax for each of the above commands, you do not have the benefit of having written that command to begin with. The intent of all those pipeline filters is not communicated to the reader, and unless you actually played with that command, one step at a time, at the prompt, it is unlikely you would ever know what that command does.</p>

<p><strong>Pipes, as a design feature, are central to the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Unix_philosophy">Unix way</a></strong>. They are Unix&rsquo;s killer app. Unfortunately, they <strong>mask the intent</strong> of a command sequence. They are extremely convenient to use at a prompt, but end up being <em>write-only</em>.</p>

<p>The maintainer of a script with the above command sequence in it would be well-advised to break that command into sections, or at least encapsulate the pipeline in a descriptive function, like:</p>

<p>```bash Names give the reader a clue</p>

<h1>!/usr/bin/env bash</h1>

<p>function unique_remote_connected_hosts {
  netstat -p tcp | grep -i established | awk &lsquo;{print $5}&rsquo; | awk -F'.&lsquo; &rsquo;{ $NF=&ldquo;&rdquo; } 1' | sed &rsquo;s/ /./g' | sed &rsquo;s/.$//&lsquo; | sort | uniq
}</p>

<p>unique_remote_connected_hosts
```</p>

<p>or perhaps:</p>

<p>```bash Composition helps</p>

<h1>!/usr/bin/env bash</h1>

<p>function unique_remote_connected_hosts {
  remote_connections | strip_port_number | sort | uniq
}</p>

<p>function remote_connections {
  netstat -p tcp | grep -i established | awk &lsquo;{print $5}&rsquo;
}</p>

<p>function strip_port_number {
  awk -F'.&lsquo; &rsquo;{ $NF=&ldquo;&rdquo; } 1' | sed &rsquo;s/ /./g' | sed &rsquo;s/.$//&lsquo;
}</p>

<p>unique_remote_connected_hosts
```</p>

<p>This functional composition is easy to do in a text editor, the natural habitat of a script. It is awkward and difficult to do at the prompt, which is too bad.</p>

<p>More on resolving this fundamental tension, next time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
